welcome to meditating with Chandra Vicki
I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientists at the University
of Toronto where I'd Emma Clete each and
scientifically study mindfulness related
phenomena like Insight flow mystical
experience transformative experience
higher states of consciousness the
cultivation of wisdom and the aspiration
to enlightenment in addition I've been
practicing the pasta meditation mat a
contemplation Tai Chi Chuan shiquan for
over 29 years and teaching the
profession for close to 20 years welcome
if you're joining us for the first time
you should know that this is a
progressive course the introductory
course is done if you wish to catch up
with us please check the links in this
video and you'll find you'll find sorry
I check the notes in this video and
you'll find links to previous lessons
you couldn't go through them at your own
pace and catch up to us we're now in a
more advanced stage and that means every
second Monday not this Monday but next
Monday is a Tarma day in which I teach
principles and practices that build on
the previous principles and practices
that I've taught we always mean and set
every day regardless Monday to Friday
from 9:30 to 10:00 there's a Q&A at the
end of every day but for the q and a's
for these sits please restrict the
questions to the ecology of practices
within this course for broader questions
that you might have a more philosophical
or existential or ethical nature or even
more scientific nature please come to my
general Q&A that's held the third Friday
live streamed on YouTube of every month
that'll be June 19th at 3 p.m. Eastern
Time so I have some really wonderful
news to share this is our 50th stream
together so thank you everybody for your
support and your dedication and your
participation it's been really wonderful
so if you get a chance please like this
video stream that will raise its
visibility on the YouTube algorithm and
help me to help as many people through
this course as I possibly can
I think that's everything we need to do
as I said this is just a regular City
it's one of the alternative Monday's and
so please set your phones to do not
disturb please get yourself into your
basic posture and we will begin to
practice when I say together begin
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate with your
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
okay so we have time for a few questions
here's a question from des if one tries
to define meditation from perspective of
distractions should the purpose of
meditation be one to rise above
distractions allusions to the strategy
to address the distractions in real 3 or
a mix of both address what is
addressable and ignored it was beyond
control or something else so the purpose
of distraction is definitely when your
so when I assume that what you're asking
yes is the practice of applying inquire
and mindfulness to the distractions the
purpose is not to make the distractions
go away the purpose is to become aware
of any of patterns that the distractions
are revealing patterns in mind and body
that's why you're doing within Hara and
mindfulness trying to bring
consciousness into something that is
normally operating unconsciously
automatically reactively defensively and
then what you're trying to do is like
see and try to realize in which way this
is limiting you constraining you and
where that really takes it was when
those patterns are operative in your
life you get some flexibility and
freedom so you can see through the ways
in which they might be misleading you so
it's kind of a middle path you're not
trying to eradicate them or just simply
rise above them or write you're trying
to see through them in the sense of
first becoming aware of them the
patterns alright and then looking
through them see trying to see how they
potentially limit or to store or confine
your mind and your body so that you you
get flexibility these patterns are have
a function you have them for a reason
they have adaptivity in them
and what you're trying to do is I
suppose are the metaphor I want to use
here is an even filter it's sift through
them and get a sense a more a conscious
living sense of them so that you can
well help them to help you you can help
them where come to life when they're
adaptive and learn to let go when
they're maladaptive I hope that helped
karema always good to hear from your
Karima
what are your thoughts on prostitution
using more honest and suchness as mantra
and applying regulated breathing and
steps it put it naturally to mean seems
wonderful in nature yes very much
when I when I teach you the that's
that's wonderful dream up very good when
I teach you guys the walking meditation
we'll start with something very similar
to that it's it's very much like a
pressure of practice we'll first of all
do I know that the the getting that
place between the inflow of receptive of
rough civic receptivity and awareness
the outflow of intention in action and
then that can build into a progeny
practice along the lines that you
indicate so yes very much very much the
thing about the moving practices is that
they are they provide a better built
bridge to your everyday life so mark the
fab welcome mark as always it's great to
have you here sometimes I pop out of
meditation into an integrated peaceful
mode of being often without achieving my
sip objective any suggestions is this
okay so that's interesting so does that
mean you sort of get this fish tall -
you have a gestalt awareness where your
attention is simultaneously inside and
outside simultaneously and beyond inside
and outside simultaneously mental and
physical and beyond them and it sort of
it feels like it has you know gathered
together it is that's what you're saying
I I would say that if if that arises
independent of what ever intention you
set freer for yourself and your set that
that's a state that is trying to become
natural for you it's it's it's it's a
way in which like like I say that the
your Buddha nature as your second nature
is starting to come through to fruition
if you just if that's what's happening
if you just sort of popping out and you
just sort of feel nice and pleasant then
that should be treated as a distraction
in return but if you're getting this
data described which is this this state
um well it's it's basically the state of
a spontaneous kind of Praja then relax
into that I don't write in the sense of
route into it not you know relax away
from it but route into it and make that
your practice make you practice of just
almost like when you learned initially
to savor your route and save your Center
just savor it because the the point here
is that you are now being you're now a
vehicle for affording it and you are
trying to more and more aspire into it I
hope that's helpful and like I said so
if it's the fur trade like I said if
it's more of this sort of spontaneous
Praja then drop whatever other intent
you have for your practice and then live
into that live into that but if it's
just simple you come out you just feel
it's sort of good and peaceful and sort
of contentedness that's just a
distraction it's one of the most
insidious ones that the monkey mind can
use to take you out of meditation every
just oh I just feel very nice oh this is
pleasant that's a distraction and you
need to return to your breath
Matthew McCready with some good weather
recently I've done a few sips outdoors
in nature there sitting outdoors afford
anything to a practice then sitting
indoors doesn't I generally that's very
brave of you Matthew maybe it's because
where we're at right now generally I
don't recommend for novices to sit
outdoors because it tends to be too
challenging I had a whole month I think
it was about four or five years into my
practice where
outdoors and it's very because it's very
difficult because once you've been
sitting for silent not moving for like
four or five minutes everything thinks
you're dead
you know insects land on new things
crawl over you I had a guy I was I was
sitting near a tree he was on one of
those big walk and he coming cut grass
right around me so I generally recommend
that it's it's not something you should
do as a novice and you can do it outside
what you can do is you can do this
practice and then move into a thing and
what you should do is you should go onto
my channel and see if some of the
discussions I've had with rage Kelly or
actually even better go into Rafe's
Channel and he has an outdoor of
practice called sit spotting so I would
you would do basically get into
everything I've taught you I think as a
way of increasing your sensitivity and
alertness and then what you do is you
then change your attention outward and
you try you keep your eyes closed but
you're trying to listen to everything
that's happened and you're listening to
bird song you're listening to thing move
things moving about and what this does
is this really enlivens your ability to
pick up on complex dynamic patterns in
your environment in an integrated and
flowing fashion so I would recommend
like I said my general recommendation
for analysis is don't sit outside
initially but if you working for you do
this practice find your core for perhaps
do a basic the past month or a basic
nutta or maybe even a bit of Praja and
then once you've gone into raves channel
or looked at some of the videos i've
done with him and he talks about sit
spotting you could try this it's funning
practice I think it's a really excellent
recommendation human ease rage five nice
to meet you
sometimes I find it difficult to
maintain mindfulness in everyday life it
becomes very exhausting till I feel like
burning out on mindfulness especially in
retreats this can be very hard yes I
strongly recommend for people who are
learning to not go into retreat until
they've been practicing seriously in a
diligent manner with a Sangha for a
minimum of a year retreats I think are
Retreat is like trying to immediately
leap into the Olympics it's it's it's
often very punishing and causes burnout
and release too much too fast and often
the people that are leading the treats
I'm sorry but I think this is a
legitimate criticism they do not have
the requisite psychological and
psychotherapeutic training they just
have what their tradition has given them
and that's not always sufficient for
what can come up for people there's a
lot of things that I would say take your
time I recommend not trying to be
mindful all day initially because you
it's that's forcing it that's not the
middle path what you're trying to do is
cultivate it so that it comes second
nature
so I recommend picking a picking what's
called a trigger I have things in my
pocket so when I put my hands in my
pocket I feel them this is a practice
some people hope the sound of a bell or
when they walk through a doorway or when
they see their own hands and what those
you pick a flag and wet one but it
happens that's when you do like maybe a
four or five five breath meditation you
know get your basic sense of being
centered rooted feeling the flow in your
body
and then follow your breath for a few
breaths of mindfulness and then see how
much you can naturally let it integrate
with what's happening around you and
then just start moving into your day and
then just repeat that through the day
and what you're doing is you're trying
to cultivate mindfulness so that it will
grow off of its own accord you try and
sort of constantly keep yourself in it
as you said it will be very very
exhausting Keira Crowther you mentioned
wisdom of my patient during an
introduction of Luxio team you know I
feel drawn to the text and you mentioned
it would come up more is that a text
that you'll come back to yes I intend to
come back to that in a bit because what
we're going to do as we move into we're
going to do some of these advanced
classes and then as we start moving
towards the wisdom Sangha
we're going to take the width of an IPA
a course very analogous to the course we
did the 10-week course we did which was
very much from sort of a Buddhist Dallas
perspective and then the wisdom of
Hypatia is the wisdom cultivation
practices and the philosophical
framework from the Western tradition
which is largely you know the the the
tradition that comes out of Socrates the
the epicurean stoic and most importantly
the Neoplatonic tradition I'm going to
follow that through so we're definitely
going to come to that we're definitely
going to come to that I would recommend
if you're feeling drawn to the text to
not immediately leap into it but I would
recommend getting the two texts by
Arthur vers Lewis that I recommend it to
you because they will give you more of
sort of a philosophical framework so
that will help to bridge what you're
learning here into the wisdom of my pace
your course but it's definitely of
course we're going to do together and
then what what you should have is sort
of these two very comprehensive I don't
like these adjectives because they're
born out of colonialism but I don't know
what adjectives to use that we'd have
basically an Eastern Rite though Eastern
wisdom traditions that I've been
teaching you inform by cognitive science
and then the Western wisdom tradition
informed by cognitive science and then
these are the two great lenses the two
great eyes by which we get the
stereoscopic you know ontological depth
perception into the depths of the world
and into the depths of ourselves and
it's also a way of trying to afford a
lived basis by which we can talk to many
different groups of people engaged in
many different practices and that of
course is much needed in the world today
thank you very much for joining us
always I want to thank my dear friend in
techno Myanmar
my beloved son Jason who was running
around behind the scenes shutting
windows and turning off tops and trying
to get that ambient sound down I really
appreciate that
again thank you for making this our 50th
class together thank you so much please
subscribe to the channel to be notified
of the next video on the channel you
will find also links to the lecture
series awaiting for the meeting crisis
the discussion series voices with Rob
aching both of them develop many of
these ideas in depth and a more
comprehensive integrated fashion invite
others who might benefit from this to
join this series they all of the lessons
are available they can always catch up
at their own pace
there's a wonderful welcoming Sangha
here and speaking of this saying that
this thing of plugs into is connected
right and I think really good friendship
with a saying a community that is
growing on the discord server Brett is
here pleasure of doubt and he will be
there the people are there they've sat
together and I will take this up and you
can discuss there's also just the
broader community here discussing all of
these things they were talking about in
depth you'll also find some wonderful
conversations with other people that
have been on voices with very baking
like paul van der kleine about greg on
reeks that's it's just a tremendous
resource and i strongly recommend it if
you can as soon as we we come out of
here go back in maybe just re quickly
resent her reroute reflow we focus maybe
just a bit of whatever practice you did
today but passing a meadow or Praja and
then do your lectio divina
i set your intention i do right for
transformation for reverence to write
the in active engagement do the embodied
emotion then do the ecstatic right the
existential ethic i should say and then
move into the ecstatic eternal remember
continuity of practice more important in
quantity there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body no friend no ally
greater than your own
minded buddy be lamps unto yourselves
take care everyone I'll see you tomorrow